Register of the Howard R. Cottam Papers 1935-1980
Hoover Institution Archives
- AMBASSADOR TO KUWAIT, 1963-1969
  - Speeches and writings of Howard R. Cottam, (consisting mainly of typewritten texts and printed copies), 1963-1969
    - Notes for American Women's League, handwritten notes, May 30, 1966 (Folder 29)
    - International School of Kuwait Faculty, handwritten notes, March 30, 1966 (Folder 30)
    - Commencement speech, International School of Kuwait, Includes drafts and program, June 6, 1966. (Folder 31)
    - Independence Day Message, Gazelle Club, Kuwait, July 4, 1966 (Folder 32)
    - "The U.S. Foreign Service," Foreign Service Institute, March 17, 1969 (Folder 33)
    - Commencement address, International School of Kuwait, June 3, 1969 (Folder 34)
    - "Status of Women in Kuwait," typewritten memorandum, June 30, 1969 (Folder 35)
  - Speeches made in honor of H. R. Cottam, 1963-1969
    - "A Chat with the American Ambassador," by Sawt Al- Khalij (Voice of the Gulf), June 11, 1964 (Folder 36)
    - Speech by the Foreign Minister of the State of Kuwait, upon the ocassion of the departure of Ambassador Cottam, ca. 1969 (Folder 37)
    - Speech by the Ambassador of the Algerian Democratic and People's Republic to Kuwait and Dean of the Diplomatic Corps, on the occasion of the departure of Ambassador Cottam, June 29, 1969 (Folder 38)
  - Collected speeches, 1963-1967
    - Fourth of July Address, President Lyndon B. Johnson, undated (Folder 39)
    - Text of Sisco Security Council Statement, undated (Folder 40)
    - Thanksgiving Proclamation, President Lyndon B. Johnson (Folder 41)
    - H. H. the Emir, Speech of Opening of the 2nd Session of the National Assembly, October 29, 1963 (Folder 42)
    - Armstrong, Willis C., Annual Dinner of the Institute of Petroleum, Grosvenor House, February 17, 1965 (Folder 43)
    - Hughes, Thomas L.
      - "Relativity in Foreign Policy: The Storage and Retrieval of Conviction," Stanford University, November 14, 1966 (Folder 44)
      - "Whose Century," Columbia University, April 14, 1967 (Folder 45)
  - Collected writings, reports, and booklets, 1963-1969
    - Cleveland, Harlan, "The Road Back to Internationalism." Reprint from The Atlantic Monthly, May 1969. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Dickson, H. R. P., "Arab Ritual of Coffee Making." Excerpt from The Arab of the Desert. (Folder 2)
    - Fenelon, Dr. K. G.
      - "Kuwait: Past and Present," undated. (Folder 3)
      - "Kuwait Sixty Years Ago," undated. (Folder 4)
      - "The Trucial States: A Brief Economic Survey," undated. (Folder 5)
    - Howard, Harry N. "Book Reviews: The Middle East in Paperback," reprint from The Middle East Journal, Summer 1974. (Folder 6)
  - Subject file, 1963-1969
    - Cottam, Katherine S.
      - Foreign Service Institute (Folder 7)
      - Polyglot Language School (Folder 8)
      - Women's Leagues and Associations (Folder 9)
    - Kuwait
      - General information booklets (Folder 10-11)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 12)
    - Middle East
      - American Embassy, Beirut, Lebanon (Folder 13)
      - Istanbul
      - Palestine Archaeological Museum
      - Turkey
    - Palestine Refugees. Report, 1966 (Folder 14)
    - Presentation of credentials to the Emir (Folder 15)
    - Silver chest - inquiries and purchase (Folder 16)
    - Travel
      - Itineraries, 1963-1969 (Folder 17)
      - U.S. Army Special Warfare Center, September 1963 (Folder 18)
      - United States, consultation trip, July-August 1967 (Folder 19)
      - Visas and miscellany (Folder 20)
    - U. S. Embassy
      - Diplomatic corps (Folder 21)
      - Information booklets (Folder 22)
      - Letters of appreciation to personnel (Folder 23)
      - Organization charts (Folder 24)
- FOOD AND AGRICULTURE ORGANIZATION OF THE U. N., 1969-1974
  - Chronological file of conferences and speeches, 1969-1974
    - White House Conference on Food, Nutrition and Health, Correspondence, December 1969. 1969-1971 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - International Development Conference, Correspondence, February 25-26, 1970. 1970 (Folder 2)
    - Animal Health Institute, Boca Raton, Florida, Correspondence, April 28, 1970. 1970 (Folder 3)
    - World Food Conference, The Hague, Correspondence, June 16-30, 1970. 1960-1971 (Folder 4)
    - White House Conference on Children, Correspondence, December 13-18, 1970. 1970 (Folder 5)
    - National Farmers Union Annual Convention, Washington, D.C., Correspondence, February 24-27, 1971. 1971-1972 (Folder 6)
    - Midwest Conference on World Affairs, Kearney, Nebraska, Correspondence, April 21, 1971. 1971-1973 (Folder 7)
    - National Limestone Institute Annual Conference, Washington, D.C., Correspondence, January 24-26, 1972. 1971 (Folder 8)
    - National Farmers Union Annual Conference, Houston, Texas, Correspondence, February 29, 1972. 1972-1974 (Folder 9)
    - Washington Institute of Foreign Affairs, Washington, D.C., Correspondence, October 24, 1972. 1972-1973 (Folder 10)
    - Fifth Annual Conference of the African and Middle East Studies Programme, University of Colorado, Correspondence, October 26-27, 1972. 1972 (Folder 11)
    - Association of U.S. University Directors of Inter- national Agricultural Programs, Cornell University, Correspondence, June 13-15, 1973. 1973 (Folder 12)
    - International Development Conference, Washington, D.C., Correspondence, October 23-25, 1973. 1972-1973 (Folder 13)
    - Agency for International Development, American University, Interview transcript, December 12, 1973. 1973 (Folder 14)
    - Institute on World Affairs, Iowa State University, Correspondence, December 10, 1973. 1973 (Folder 15)
    - Farm and Industrial Equipment Institute meeting, Correspondence, January 17, 1974. 1974 (Folder 16)
    - "World Focus on Food," Western Governors' Conference on Agriculture, April 17, 1974 (Folder 17)
    - Association of U.S. University Directors of Inter- national Agricultural Programs, Cornell University, Correspondence, June 5-7, 1974. 1974 (Folder 18)
    - American Dietetic Association, Chicago, Illinois (?), Correspondence, October 1974. 1974 (Folder 19)
    - Symposium on World Food and Population, American University, Washington, D.C., Correspondence and program, October 7-8, 1974. 1974 (Folder 20)
    - Cincinnati Council on World Affairs, Correspondence, October 18, 1974. 1972-1974 (Folder 21)
    - World Food Conference, Rome, Italy, Correspondence, reports, articles, memoranda, November 5-16, 1974. 1973-1974 (Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1974
    - General, 1970-1974 (Folder 23)
    - General, congratulatory, 1970-1974 (Folder 24)
    - American Near East Refugee Aid, Inc. (ANERA), 1972 (Folder 25)
    - American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, 1972 (Folder 26)
    - Archer, Angus, 1970 (Folder 27)
    - Beaty, Layne, 1970 (Folder 28)
    - Commission on Critical Choices for Americans (Michael J. Deutch), 1974 (Folder 29)
    - Crockett, William J., 1970 (Folder 30)
    - Draper, Gen. William, 1973 (Folder 31)
    - Ensminger, Douglas, 1974 (Folder 32)
    - Fluor, Mrs. J. S., 1974 (Folder 33)
    - Forbes, Reginald, 1971 (Folder 34)
    - Hardin, Dr. Lowell S., 1974 (Folder 35)
    - Hughes, Thomas, 1973 (Folder 36)
    - King, Mrs. Martin Luther, 1973 (Folder 37)
    - Nelson, Dr. Lowry, 1974 (Folder 38)
    - Rampton, Governor Calvin K., 1970-1974 (Folder 39)
    - Rothenberg, Dr. M. A., 1974 (Folder 40)
    - Rusk, Dean, 1973 (Folder 41)
    - Schlesinger, James R., 1974 (Folder 42)
    - Stare, Dr. Fredrick J., 1974 (Folder 43)
    - Symmes, Dr. Harrison, 1974 (Folder 44)
    - Van Dam, Andre, 1974 (Folder 45)
    - Wallace, Robert B., 1974 (Folder 46)
    - Young, Dr. Herrick B., 1973 (Folder 47)
    - Zempel, Clara, 1974 (Folder 48)
  - Internal correspondence of the FAO, 1969-1974
    - General, 1970-1974 (Folder 49)
    - Anderson, Viggo, 1971-1972 (Folder 50)
    - Aubrac, Raymond, 1972-1974 (Folder 51)
    - Bachman, Kenneth L., 1972 (Folder 52)
    - Benaissa, Mohamed, 1974 (Folder 53)
    - Bildesheim, Gerardo E., 1970 (Folder 54)
    - Boerma, Addeke H., 1970-1973 (Folder 55)
    - Contini, Paolo, 1970 (Folder 56)
    - Crane, Peter, 1973 (Folder 57)
    - Hartmans, Ermond, 1970 (Folder 58)
    - Huyser, Jan P., 1970-1974 (Folder 59)
    - Jackson, Roy I., 1972-1974 (Folder 60)
    - Kaghan, Theodore, 1971 (Folder 61)
    - Kimmel, Don, 1974 (Folder 62)
    - Kotter, Herbert R., 1972 (Folder 63)
    - Mackenzie, Colin, 1974 (Folder 64)
    - Nehemiah, J. V. A., 1971-1974 (Folder 65)
    - Ojala, Dr. Eric, 1970-1974 (Folder 66)
    - Shefrin, Frank, 1970-1974 (Folder 67)
    - Steenberg, Dr. B. K., 1974 (Folder 68)
    - Stevenson, K. A. P., 1974 (Folder 69)
    - Stordy, John, 1973-1974 (Folder 70)
    - Trever, Pierre, 1970 (Folder 71)
    - Vidal-Naquet, Alain, 1973 (Folder 72)
    - Walton, Declan J., 1970-1974 (Folder 73)
    - Weitz, Charles, 1971-1973 (Folder 74)
    - Wells, Oris V., 1970-1971 (Folder 75)
    - West, Edward M., 1970-1973 (Folder 76)
    - Yriart, Juan-Felipe, 1972-1974 (Folder 77)
  - Subject file, 1969-1974
    - American-Arab Association for Commerce and Industry, Inc. (AAACI)
      - General (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Announcements of Meetings and Events (Folder 2)
      - Assessment and Summary Report (Folder 3)
      - Correspondence
        - General (Folder 4)
        - Scanlon, Charles J. (Folder 5)
        - Yusif, I. F. (Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 7)
      - Survey of Board Members (Folder 8)
    - American Freedom from Hunger Foundation (AFFHF)
      - General (Folder 9)
      - Bulletins (Folder 10)
      - Correspondence (Folder 11)
      - Sahelian Zone (Folder 12)
    - American Independent Oil Company (AMINOIL)
      - Agribusiness in Kuwait
        - Cottam, H. R., "Aminoil Participation in Agri-Business in Kuwait: A Preliminary Assessment." (Folder 13)
        - Correspondence (Folder 14)
        - Reports and notes (Folder 15)
      - Correspondence (Folder 16)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 17)
    - American Society of Agricultural Consultants (ASAG)
      - General (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Annual Meeting, Sept. 25-27, 1977 (Folder 2)
      - Meissner, Frank
        - "Israeli Technical Cooperation in Agriculture: An Unfinished Agenda for the Third Decade." (Folder 3)
        - "Satisfying Demand for Technical Services in Agriculture of Developing Countries: A Challenge for ASAC Members." (Folder 4)
    - Aspen Institute for Humanitarian Studies. Consultation with and proposed study, 1974 (Folder 5)
    - Brookings Institution. Study and proposed symposium, 1972-1974 (Folder 6)
    - Canada. Department of Agriculture. Correspondence, 1971-1974
      - Olson, H. A., 1969-1970 (Folder 7)
      - Poirier, Rolland P., 1974 (Folder 8)
      - Williams, S. B., 1974 (Folder 9)
      - Willis, Thomas, 1970-1971 (Folder 10)
    - Consuls. Correspondence, 1969-1973
      - Byrnes, Paul J., 1973 (Folder 11)
      - Kelley, William B., Esq., 1971
      - Lawrence, Edward M., 1972
      - Ritchie, A. Edgar, 1969
      - Schmidt, Eugene T., 1971
      - Shaikh, M., 1971
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research. Correspondence and letter of agreement, 1974 (Folder 12)
    - Control Data Corporation (Folder 13)
    - Daniel, Mann, Johnson, and Mendenhall (DMHM) - SAPTCO (Folder 14)
    - Diplomatic and Consular Officers, Retired (DACOR). Proposed luncheon series, 1973 (Folder 15)
    - Evergreen Helicopters - Wendell Wyatt (Folder 16)
    - Fertilizers. Correspondence and memorandum, 1973-1974 (Folder 17)
    - Flying Scotsman, Inc. (Folder 18)
    - General Mining and Construction Company/Maxon Construction (Folder 19)
    - Harding Livestock and Land Company (Folder 20)
    - Industry Cooperative Program (FAO). Correspondence, 1973 (Folder 21)
    - International agriculture adjustment. Correspondence, studies, notes, 1971-1974 (Folder 22)
    - League for International Food Education (Folder 23)
    - Liaison Office for North America, Washington, D.C. (LNOR) (Folder 24)
    - Miscellany. Memoranda, lists, etc. (Folder 25)
    - Pesticides. Correspondence, reports, memoranda, articles, 1973-1974 (Folder 26)
    - U.S.-Arab Business Development Association (USABDA) (Folder 27)
    - U.S. Congress. Correspondence
      - House of Representatives. Seiberling, John F., M.C., 1974 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Senate
        - Anderson, Clinton P., 1972 (Folder 2)
        - Bentsen, Lloyd, n.d. (Folder 3)
        - Ervin, Sam J., Jr., 1974 (Folder 4)
        - Miller, Jack R., 1973 (Folder 5)
        - Proxmire, William, 1973 (Folder 6)
    - U.S. Department of Agriculture. Correspondence, 1970-1974
      - Brunthaver, Carroll G., 1972 (Folder 7)
      - Butz, Earl, 1973-1974 (Folder 8)
      - Cowden, Thomas, 1974 (Folder 9)
      - Harris, Dwight, 1971 (Folder 10)
      - Hardin, Clifford M., 1970-1971 (Folder 11)
      - Kellogg, Charles E., 1970 (Folder 12)
      - Paarlberg, Dr. Don, 1971-1973 (Folder 13)
      - Phillips, Dr. Ralph W., 1970-1974 (Folder 14)
      - Upchurch, Dr. Louis, 1971 (Folder 15)
      - Yeutter, Clayton, 1974 (Folder 16)
    - U.S. Department of State. Correspondence, 1970-1974
      - Armstrong, Willis C., 1972 (Folder 17)
      - Caton, Douglas D., 1970 (Folder 18)
      - Claxton, Philander P., Jr., 1970 (Folder 19)
      - DePalma, Samuel, 1972-1973 (Folder 20)
      - Hannah, Dr. John A., 1969-1974 (Folder 21)
      - Haugerud, Howard E., 1974 (Folder 22)
      - Hertz, Martin, 1974 (Folder 23)
      - Martin, Edwin M., 1974 (Folder 24)
      - Schaler, Otto, 1974 (Folder 25)
      - Tubby, Roger, 1970 (Folder 26)
      - Williams, Maurice J., 1970 (Folder 27)
      - Wolle, William E., 1974 (Folder 28)
    - World Food Institute - proposed World Food Conference, 1976 (Folder 29)
- INTERNATIONAL CONSULTANT (POST-RETIREMENT), 1974-1984
  - Chronological file of conferences and speeches, 1974-1984
    - General. Letters, schedules, receipts, 1975-1980. (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - Conference on Foreign Policy in the United States, Washington Public Affairs Center and University of Southern California, Washington D.C., Schedule and notes, January 28-30, 1975. 1975 (Folder 31)
    - "Toward a U.S. National Policy on Global Hunger," A Consultation to Farmers, Waverly, Iowa, Correspondence, speech text, notes, program, February 28-29, 1975. 1975 (Folder 32)
    - "Need We Contemplate World-Wide Hunger?" Windham College Lecture Series, Windham County, Vermont, Correspondence, speech text and program, March 6, 1975. 1975 (Folder 33)
    - Commission for the Observance of World Population Year, Seminar: Population, Food and Related Issues, Deputy Chair/Coordinator, Reston, Virginia, April 4-5, 1975 (Folder 34)
    - Baltimore Annual Conference of the United Methodist Church, Conference: Peace and Self-Detemination of Peoples, Baltimore, Maryland, Correspondence and program, May 27-29, 1975. 1974-1975 (Folder 35)
    - St. Andrew's Episcopal Church, Monday Night Discussion Groups, Correspondence and speech notes, June 30, 1975. 1975 (Folder 36)
    - U.S.-Middle East Agri-business Potential Conference, California State College, Stanislaus, Turlock, California, Speech text, correspondence, program, October 16-17, 1975. 1975 (Folder 37)
    - Junior Science and Humanities Symposium, Georgetown University, Washington D.C., Program, correspondence, January 9-10, 1976. 1976 (Folder 38)
    - Delmarva Conference on Hunger, University of Delaware, Program, schedule, correspondence, April 2-3, 1976. 1976 (Folder 39)
    - Center for Strategic and International Studies, World Affairs Council of Philadelphia, Program, correspondence, and schedule, May 12, 1976. 1976 (Folder 40)
    - Luncheon for Secretary of Agriculture Earl Butz, Washington Institute of Foreign Affairs, Transcript of speech and correspondence, May 24, 1976. 1976 (Folder 41)
    - The Cooperative Forum, Washington D.C., Schedule and program, May 19, 1976. 1976 (Folder 42)
    - Allied Social Science Association Annual Meeting, Atlantic City, New Jersey, Program, bulletins, correspondence, September 16-18, 1976. 1976 (Folder 43)
    - "Problems and Prospects of Agribusiness in the Middle East," The Middle East Institute, Washington D.C., Correspondence, speech text, program, September 27-28, 1976. 1976 (Folder 44)
    - "The Politics of Food," The Foreign Affairs Inter- departmental Seminar, Rosslyn, Virginia, Correspondence and program, January 18, 1977. 1976-1977 (Folder 45)
    - Agricultural Trade Council, Washington D.C., Statements made by the Agricultural Trade Council, correspondence, program, April 5-6, 1977. 1977 (Folder 46)
    - International Center for Dynamics of Development, Luncheon-Symposium on Lebanon, The Brookings Institution, Washington, D.C., Printed matter, June 19, 1977. 1977 (Folder 47)
    - "Search for Quality Through a Doctrine of Global Nutritional Adequacy," Soroptimist International, Washington, D.C., Correspondence and speech text, July 29, 1977. 1977 (Folder 48)
    - "G.A.O. and Food Planning: Global Nutritional Adequacy, The Target," United States General Accounting Office, Washington, D.C. Notes for presentation, correspondence, draft of final report, March 22, 1977. 1977 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - "Petromarkets '79," Mid-Asia/Africa Business Company (MABCO), Atlanta, Georgia, Correspondence, notes, clippings, October 9-14, 1978. 1978 (Folder 2)
    - Conference sponsored by the Chamber of Commerce of the United States and the Chicago Association of Commerce and Industry, Chicago, Illinois, Correspondence, synopsis, notes, June 18-19, 1979. 1979 (Folder 3)
    - "Arab Commerce 1980," Mid-Asia/Africa Business Company (MABCO), Dallas, Texas, Program, speech notes, correspondence, October 2-5, 1979. 1979 (Folder 4)
  - Collected writing. Wilson, Thomas L., "Food and Gover- nance," prepared for the Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies and the General Services Foundation, 1978. (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1979
    - General (Folder 6)
    - Department of State, 1977 (Folder 7)
    - Johnson, Frances B., 1978 (Folder 8)
  - Miscellany (Folder 9)
  - Subject file, 1975-1984
    - Condolences. Death of Howard R. Cottam, 1984 (Folder 10)
    - Food System Development. A proposal by U.S. Agency for International Development, 1977 (Folder 11)
    - International Encyclopedia of Higher Education. Proposed article agreement; report by Robert C. Tetro, 1976 (Folder 12)
    - Multinational Agribusiness Systems Incorporated. Correspondence, bulletins, 1976 (Folder 13)
    - PANTEC/TADCO
      - Citrus Products Information (Folder 14)
      - Correspondence
        - Moakler, Alfred, 1976 (Folder 15)
        - Waters, Herbert, 1976
      - Reports (Folder 16)
    - Pantograf. A proposed movie production, 1975 (Folder 17)
    - Satellite cities. (Folder 18)
    - Society for International Development Survey, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - U.S. - Arab Business Development Association. Correspondence and article of incorporation, 1979 (Folder 2)
    - U.S. - Arab liaison infra-structures. Report prepared by Winters and Associates, 1979. (Folder 3)
    - U.S. Objectives in the Food and Agriculture Organization, U.S. - F.A.O. Interagency Committee. Report and correspondence, 1976 (Folder 4)
    - World Food Systems, Incorporated
      - Correspondence (Folder 5)
      - Reports (Folder 6)
  - Writings, 1976-1977
    - Commission to Study the Organization of Peace. Proposal revisions, 1976 (Folder 7)
    - "U.S. Participation in International Organizations," written for the General Accounting Office, Includes correspondence and written drafts., 1977. (Folder 8)
- DECLASSIFIED RECORDS, 1964-1975 (Box 18)
  Formerly security-classified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover
  - 2011 July release of records, 1964-1975
    - U.S. ambassador to Kuwait letters and cables, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - North American representative/FAO letters and notes, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 18: 2-6)
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE, 1933- circa 1980
  - 19 prints, depicting the career of Howard R. Cottam in Italy and Brazil, 1933-1963 (Envelope A)
  - 20 prints depicting the career of Howard R. Cottam, in Kuwait, 1963-circa 1980 (Envelope B)